（讲师）欢迎回来。
(Lecturer) Welcome back.
现在，随着我们不断进步
Now, as we keep progressing
通过这个 CSS 基础部分，
through this CSS fundamentals section,
有几个基本的
there are a couple of fundamental
和非常重要的理论概念
and really important theoretical concepts
你真的需要明白
that you really need to understand
为了最终掌握CSS。
in order to eventually master CSS.
因此，本节包含五个理论讲座，
Therefore, this section contains five theory lectures,
这是第一个。
and this one is the first one.
而这一切都与发生的事情有关
And it's all about what happens
当有多个 CSS 规则时
when there are multiple CSS rules
适用于相同的元素。
that apply to the same elements.
因此，到目前为止，我们已经编写了代码，
So, as we have written our code until this point,
我们创造了几种情况
we have created a couple of situations
其中多个 CSS 选择器，
in which multiple CSS selectors,
因此，多个 CSS 规则，
and, therefore, multiple CSS rules,
适用于完全相同的元素。
apply to the exact same element.
我称之为冲突选择器。
And I call that conflicting selectors.
所以现在让我们了解会发生什么
So let's now learn what happens
在这样的情况下。
in situations like that.
所以，这里有一个例子
So, here is an example
这类似于代码
that is similar to the code
我们在项目中写的。
that we wrote in our project.
所以这是作者段
So it's the author paragraph
我们在代码中的某个地方，
that we have somewhere in the code,
但这里我们有一个名为“author-text”的 ID
but here we have one ID called "author-text,"
还有一类叫做“作者”。
and one class called "author."
然后，在右侧，
And then, on the right side,
我们有三个规则
we have three rules
实际应用于此元素。
that are actually applied to this element.
所以，我们可以清楚地看到，
So, as we can clearly see,
所有这三个不同的选择器，
all of these three different selectors,
因此，所有这三个规则，
and, therefore, all of these three rules,
都选择相同的元素。
all select the same element.
所以现在，最大的问题是，
And so now, the big question is,
哪些规则适用？
which of these rules applies?
嗯，这个问题的答案
Well, the answer to that
实际上是所有这些都适用。
is actually that all of them apply.
所以，所有规则
So, all rules
以及规则中的所有属性
and all the properties that are in the rules
应用于此元素。
are applied to this element.
但是，如果我们仔细观察，我们可以看到
However, if we take a close look, we can see
存在冲突的字体大小声明。
that there are conflicting font-size declarations.
对？
Right?
所以在第一个中，
So in the first one,
它说字体大小应该是18，
it says the font size should be 18,
然后是 20 像素，
then 20 pixels,
然后是 22 像素。
and then 22 pixels.
那么会是哪一个呢？
So which of those is it gonna be?
会不会是18岁
Will it be 18,
20 还是 22 像素？
00:02:09,150 --> 00:02:12,870
好吧，让我们学习一下 CSS 应用的规则
20 or 22 pixels?
Well, let's learn what rules CSS applies
为了解决冲突的声明
in order to resolve conflicting declarations
像这个。
like this one.
所以，当有多个声明时
So, when there are multiple declarations
对于完全相同的元素，
for the exact same element,
就像我们在我们的例子中看到的那样，
such as we have here in our example,
那么重要的是选择器。
then what matters are the selectors.
所以目前最高优先级是 ID 选择器。
So the highest priority for now are the ID selectors.
这意味着如果有任何 ID 选择器，
So that means if there is any ID selector,
那么这就是将要应用的规则。
then that is the rule that is going to be applied.
现在，如果有多个 ID 选择器，
Now, if there are multiple ID selectors,
那么它是这些选择器中的最后一个
then it is the last of those selectors
得到应用。
that gets applied.
现在，在现实中，
Now, in reality,
它实际上比这更复杂一些。
it is actually a bit more complicated than this.
所以涉及到很多概念
So, there are a lot of concepts involved
比如级联
such as the cascade
和选择器特异性，
and selector specificity,
但你现在不需要知道这些细节
but you don't need to know about these details for now
作为初学者。
as a beginner.
所以我认为信息量
So I think that the amount of information
我将在这张幻灯片中给你
that I will give you in this slide
应该足以让您解决自己的冲突
should be enough for you to resolve your own conflicts
在您自己的 CSS 代码中。
in your own CSS code.
好的。
All right.
但是，无论如何，万一没有 ID 选择器，
But, anyway, in case there is no ID selector,
然后是优先级中的下一个
then the next in the priority
是一个类或伪类选择器。
is a class or a pseudo-class selector.
而且，再一次，如果有多个，
And, again, if there are multiple ones of those,
那么它是代码中的最后一个选择器
then it is the last selector of those in the code
得到应用。
that gets applied.
然后，接下来是元素选择器。
Then, the next is the element selector.
所以万一没有ID选择器
So in case there is no ID selector
或者没有类选择器，
or no class selector,
然后它是被应用的元素选择器。
then it is the element selector that gets applied.
而且，再次，如果有多个，
And, again, if there are multiple,
这是最后一个。
it is the last one of those.
最后，还有一点
Finally, there's also something
称为通用选择器，
called the universal selector,
但更多的是关于那个
but a bit more about that
在接下来的讲座中。
in the next lecture.
重要的是通用选择器
What matters is that the universal selector
是所有优先级最低的。
is the one with the lowest priority of all.
好的？
All right?
但是现在，回到我们的例子，
But now, going back to our example,
并考虑到
and taking into consideration
我们在这里的规则，
the rules that we have here,
我们现在应该能够解决冲突
we should now be able to resolve the conflict
我们在这里。
that we have here.
所以我们有一个类选择器，
So we have a class selector,
然后我们有一个 ID 选择器，
then we have an ID selector,
然后我们有一个元素选择器，对吧？
and then we have an element selector, right?
所以，根据我们刚刚在这里学到的规则，
So, based on the rules that we just learned here,
它是 ID 为“author-text”的 ID 选择器
it is the ID selector with the ID of "author-text"
这将决定这个元素的字体大小。
that will decide the font size of this element.
因此，对于冲突的 font-size 属性，
So, for the conflicting font-size property,
就是这个 ID 选择器
it is this ID selector
这实际上得到了应用。
that actually gets applied.
但请记住，字体样式，
But keep in mind that the font style,
字体系列和颜色
font family, and the color
从所有其他选择器仍然适用，对吧？
from all the other selectors still applies, right?
这就是我在上一张幻灯片中提到的内容。
So that's what I mentioned in the last slide.
所以，如果我们有多个规则，
So, if we have multiple rules,
因此，选择相同元素的多个选择器，
so, multiple selectors that select the same element,
那么所有这些规则都适用。
then all of those rules apply.
所以这里的这些规则
So these rules here
仅用于解决冲突的属性，
are only for resolving the conflicting properties,
例如在这种情况下的字体大小，
such as the font size in this case,
因为，再次，
because, again,
字体大小存在
the font size is present
在目前适用的所有三个规则中
in all the three rules that are applying right now
到我们的作者元素。
to our author element.
好的。
All right.
这些是最重要的规则
And these are the most important rules
你需要知道的
that you need to know
解决冲突的声明。
to resolve conflicting declarations.
但是，为了完整起见，
But, just for the sake of completeness,
其实有些东西
there are actually things
具有更高优先级的
that have a higher priority
比 ID 选择器。
than the ID selector.
所以其中之一就是内联样式。
So one of those things is inline styles.
所以，记住我们声明了内联样式
So, remember that we declare inline styles
通过使用 HTML 中的 style 属性。
by using the style attribute in HTML.
现在，既然我们实际上不应该这样做，
Now, since we shouldn't actually do this anyway,
这不是很重要，
this is not really important,
但你还是应该知道
but you should still know
这些样式实际上具有优先权
that these styles actually have priority
使用 ID 选择器声明的样式。
over the styles that are declared using an ID selector.
然后，以最高优先级，
Then, with the highest priority,
我们有用重要关键字标记的声明。
we have declarations marked with the important keyword.
而重要的关键字基本上只是一个hack
And the important keyword is basically just a hack
你可以作为最后的手段
that you can use as a last resort
解决 CSS 中的冲突。
to resolve conflicts in your CSS.
但这通常不应该使用。
But this should usually not be used.
所以，正如我提到的，
So, as I mentioned,
它应该只作为你最后的手段。
it should only be as your last resort.
但重要的是，这确实是最高优先级
But what matters is that this really is the highest priority
可以存在的。
that can exist.
每当我们用重要标记声明时，
Whenever we mark a declaration with important,
它将被应用。
it is the one that will be applied.
好的。
Okay.
说了这么多，
And with all that being said,
现在让我们回到我们的代码
let's now jump back into our code
并在实践中实际看到这一点。
and actually see this in practice.
让我们创建一个非常简单的例子
And let's create a very simple example
与页脚中的这一段。
with this paragraph that is in the footer.
所以，现在，在这里，我们添加了“版权”的ID，
So, right now, here, we have added the ID of "copyright",
但现在让我们也给它添加一个类。
but let's now also add a class to it.
所以只是为了创建一种类似的例子
So just to create a kind of similar example
我们在幻灯片中的内容。
to what we had in the slide.
所以，我在这里添加了一类“版权”。
So, here I'm adding a class of "copyright."
因此，一个类可以具有与 ID 完全相同的名称。
So a class can have the exact same name as the ID.
这根本不是问题。
That's not a problem at all.
现在我要做点什么
And now I will do something
我们以前实际上没有这样做，
that we actually didn't do before,
这是添加另一个类。
which is to add another class.
所以我们实际上可以添加多个类，
So we can actually add multiple classes,
我们所要做的就是添加一个空格。
and all we have to do is to just add a space.
所以我还要添加“文本”类。
So I will also add the class of "text."
所以现在这个既有“版权”的类别
And so now this one has both the class of "copyright"
和“文本”，好吗？
and of "text," all right?
因此，我们将能够选择元素
So, we will be able to select the element
使用它们。
using both of them.
所以，让我们在这里尝试这样做。
So, let's try to do that here.
在末尾，
At the end,
我将在这里添加另一个评论，
I will just add another comment here,
“解决冲突。”
"resolving conflicts."
因此，让我们尝试为该文本添加一些不同的颜色。
So let's try to add some different colors to this text.
所以，在这里，我要说，“版权”
So, here, I'm going to say, "copyright"
并将其设置为红色，
and set it to red,
然后“版权”类，
then "copyright" the class,
在这里设置为蓝色。
set it here to blue.
然后是“文本”类，
Then the class of "text,"
在这里设置为黄色。
set it to yellow here.
最后，我还将使用元素来选择它。
And, finally, I'm also going to select it using elements.
所以我会在这里使用后代选择器，
So I'll use the descendant selector here,
“页脚”，然后是“p”
"footer," and then "p,"
所以我将简单地选择“p”元素
so I will simply select the "p" element
这是页脚的内部。
that's inside of the footer.
但请记住，这些仍然是元素。
But keep in mind that these are still elements.
所以在这里，我将应用绿色。
And so here, I will apply the green color.
所以，现在，我们有这四个规则，
So, right now, we have these four rules,
所以这四个选择器，
and so these four selectors,
应用于该元素。
that are applying to that element.
那么你认为文字会有什么颜色呢？
So which color do you think the text will have?
好，
Well,
让我们来看看。
let's see.
而且，确实，它是红色的。
And, indeed, it is red.
这是因为我们这里有一个 ID 选择器，
And so that's because we have an ID selector here,
并且 ID 选择器具有更高的优先级
and the ID selector has a higher priority
比，例如，这里的这个，
than, for example, this one here,
或者这个，或者这个，
or this one, or this one,
因为这些是类选择器
because these are class selectors
这些是元素选择器。
and these are element selectors.
实际上，VS Code 帮助了我们
Actually, VS Code helps us
顺便说一句，解决这个冲突。
resolving this conflict, by the way.
所以如果我们将鼠标悬停在这个上面，我们有这个提示，
So if we hover over this, we have this hint,
上面写着“选择器特异性”。
which says, "Selector Specificity."
所以，在那里，我们在第一个位置有一个 1，
And so, there, we have a 1 in the very first position,
在这里，在课堂上，
and here, in the class,
我们在第二个位置有一个 1。
we have a 1 in the second position.
在这里，在元素中，我们有一个 2，
And here, in the element, we have a 2,
但这没关系。
but that doesn't matter.
所以它只是第三个位置的一个数字。
So it's just a number in the third position.
所以第一个位置是
And so the first position is the one
具有最高优先级。
that has the highest priority.
第二个具有第二高的优先级，
The second has the second-highest priority,
然后是元素。
and then the elements.
好的？
Okay?
现在，再次，这里还有一些规则，
Now, again, there are some more rules here,
例如，为什么有两个的原因，
for example, the reason behind why there is a two,
但我们暂时不要关注这一点。
but let's not focus on that for now.
好的？
All right?
重要的是这是一个ID
What matters is that this is an ID
因此，现在适用的是红色。
and therefore it is the red color that applies now.
我们也可以在这里看到，
We can also see that here,
在检查员中，
in the inspector,
所以在开发工具中。
so in the dev tools.
所以如果我在这里检查这个元素，
So if I inspect this element here,
那么你会发现我们需要更多的空间，
then you'll see that we need some more space here,
但你也看到了什么
but what you also see
是我们这里有这个“版权”。
is that we have this "copyright" here.
所以就是这个。
So that's this one.
我们还有这个，
We also have this other one,
来自之前
which comes from before
对于字体大小。
for the font size.
所以在这里，现在，它们都适用。
And so here, now, both of them apply.
然后我们还有其他三个。
And then we also have these other three.
所以这三个规则也在这里。
So these three rules are also here.
你看到他们都在这里
And you see that all of them here
基本上都被划掉了吧？
are basically crossed out, right?
所以他们完成了这次罢工，
So they have this strike through,
这意味着它们没有被应用。
which means that they are not being applied.
好的？
Okay?
现在，如果这里不存在这个会发生什么？
Now, what happens if this one here did not exist?
所以，如果我们在这里关闭这个，基本上。
So, if we turned this one here off, basically.
因此，这与删除此代码相同。
So, that would be the same as deleting this code.
那么，你认为那时会发生什么？
And so, what do you think would happen then?
所以在这种情况下，我们有两个类选择器
So in that case, we have two class selectors
和一个元素选择器。
and one element selector.
所以试着做出你的猜测，
So try to make your guess,
然后让我们尝试删除此代码
and then let's try to either remove this code
或取消选中此框。
or to uncheck this box.
和，
And,
是的，文字变黄了。
yeah, the text turned yellow.
以及这样做的原因
And the reason for that
是不是现在我们有了这两个选择器
is that now we have these two selectors
具有相同的层次结构，
with the same hierarchy,
所以以相同的优先级，
so with the same priority,
然后，在那种情况下，
and then, in that situation,
这是最后一个适用的。
it is the last one that applies.
所以，就是这个。
And so, that is this one.
对？
Right?
现在，如果我们关掉那个，
Now, if we turn that one off,
那么它当然是蓝色的。
then of course it would be blue.
最后，只有那时，
And, finally, only then,
如果这三个都不存在，
if none of these three existed,
然后文本将变为绿色。
then the text would become green.
所以我希望这是有道理的。
So I hope that made sense.
让我们在这里实际分析一些更多的情况。
And let's actually analyze some more situations here.
所以，例如，
So, for example,
这里的这个元素，我认为它有一个类，
this element here, I think it has a class,
或者，实际上是一个 ID。
or, actually, an ID.
所以，是的，它有一个作者ID。
So, yeah, it has an author ID.
而且，当然，它也有这个元素选择器，
And, of course, it also has this element selector,
这适用于所有段落。
which applies to all the paragraphs.
所以在这里，我们有冲突的字体大小。
And so here, we have the conflicting font size.
基本上就是这个例子
and basically that's the example
我们在幻灯片中研究过，对吧？
that we studied in the slide, right?
所以这里的这个很明显。
So this one here is pretty obvious.
那么让我们在这里看看这个h1，
Then let's check out this h1 here,
因为在这里我们有很多适用的规则，
because here we have a lot of rules that are applying,
但事实上，它们似乎并不冲突。
but, in fact, they don't seem to be conflicting.
或者，实际上，它们是冲突的。
Or, actually, they are conflicting.
所以这里的颜色应该是这个灰色
So here, the color is supposed to be this gray,
然后这里应该是这个蓝色。
and then here it is supposed to be this blue.
所以让我们去看看实际发生的地方。
So let's go up where this actually happens.
所以，
And so,
是的，这里适用的是这三个规则。
yeah, it is these three rules here that are applying.
对？
Right?
但它们都只是元素选择器。
But all of them are only element selectors.
所以没有ID，也没有类。
So there's no IDs and no classes.
因此，因此，
And so, therefore,
颜色实际上是蓝色而不是灰色的原因
the reason why the color is actually blue and not gray
是因为这里的这个选择器出现在代码的最后。
is because this selector here appears last in the code.
如果我们把这个放在第一位，
If we put this one first,
那么你会看到
then you would see
文本确实会变成灰色。
that the text would indeed become gray.
好的，但让我们把它放回去。
Okay, but let's put that back.
好的？
Okay?
现在只是最后一个例子
And now just one final example
与链接。
with the links.
所以让我们搬到这里。
So let's move down here.
还要记住我们在幻灯片中所说的，
And remember also how we said in the slide,
这些伪类实际上如何也具有优先级
how these pseudo classes actually also have priority
超过元素。
over elements.
所以，即使我们把...
And so, even if we put...
像这样，在这里。
Like this, here.
所以，如果我们选择它，锚点，
So, if we select it, the anchors,
只需在没有任何伪类的情况下执行此操作，
simply by doing this without any pseudo class,
让我们再说一次红色，
let's say color red, once again,
那么为什么
then the reason why
这对链接没有任何影响
this does not have any effect on the links
是因为这个优先级更高
is because this one has a higher priority
因为它在选择器中确实有伪类，
because it does have the pseudo class in the selector,
而这个没有。
and this one does not.
对？
Right?
所以如果我们现在在这里选择这个，
And so if we now select this here,
然后你会看到这两条规则都适用，
then you will see that both of these rules do apply,
但是颜色，正如我刚才提到的，
but the color, as I just mentioned,
当然会来自这个。
will of course come from this one.
而且，再一次，那是因为这里的这个
And, again, that's because this one here
确实有伪类，
does have the pseudo class,
而这个非常简单，是一个元素选择器。
while this one is, very simply, a element selector.
好吧，还有……
Okay, and...
是的，这是你现在需要知道的。
Yeah, this is what you need to know for now.
我们稍后会遇到其中一些情况
We will encounter some of these situations later on
当我们完成课程时，
as we go through the course,
到那时，我将对此进行更多解释，
and by then, I will explain a little bit more about this,
但现在，
but for now,
这就是我想让你知道的关于这个话题的全部内容，
this is all I wanted you to know about this topic,
这对于初学者来说可能会很混乱
which can be quite confusing for beginners
当他们开始编写自己的 CSS 代码时，
when they start writing their own CSS code,
然后规则开始冲突，
and then the rules start conflicting,
然后他们并不真正了解正在发生的事情。
and then they do not really understand what is happening.
所以我认为这很重要，
So I think that this is important,
所以希望你喜欢这个视频并发现它很有用。
and so hopefully you liked this video and found it useful.
哦，还有最后一件事
Oh, and just one final thing
我其实是想给你看的
that I actually wanted to show you
在我离开你之前，
before I leave you with this,
是“重要”的关键字。
is the "important" keyword.
所以，记住“重要”关键字
So, remember how the "important" keyword
基本上，使声明更重要，
makes a declaration more important, basically,
比所有其他的。
than all the other ones.
所以让我们回到这里。
So let's come back down here.
检查它。
Inspect it.
当然，正如我们已经看到的，
And, of course, as we already saw,
这个选择器在这里，
this selector here,
这个，是所有优先级最低的，
this one, is the one with the lowest priority of all,
因为它只是一个元素选择器。
because it's just an element selector.
但是如果我们现在在这里添加“重要”关键字，像这样，
But if we now add the "important" keyword here, like this,
所以， ”！
so, "!
重要的，”
important,"
然后，突然之间，文本将变为绿色。
then, all of a sudden, the text will become green.
对？
Right?
所以，就像你在这里看到的那样。
So, just as you can see it here.
但是，再一次，这更像是一个黑客
But, again, this is more of a hack
你不应该经常使用。
that you should not be using usually.
以防万一你真的，真的想不通
Just in case you really, really cannot figure out
您的代码中发生了什么。
what's happening in your code.
但即便如此，而不是使用“重要”关键字，
00:16:37,180--> 00:16:38,700
你应该怎么做
But even then, instead of using the "important" keyword,
what you should probably do
是编写更简单的选择器。
is to write simpler selectors.
所以这也是一个重要的规则
So this is also an important rule
和一个重要的外卖
and an important takeaway
你应该从这个讲座中得到。
that you should take from this lecture.
所以，总是尽可能简单地编写你的选择器，
So, always write your selectors as simple as possible,
并且不要添加过多的嵌套，
and do not add too much nesting,
或者不要添加太多ID
or don't add too many IDs
和班级
and classes
都在同一个选择器中，好吗？
all in the same selector, okay?
所以我会把它留在这里给你，
So I will leave that here for you,
但我会评论出来
but I will comment it out
所以它不适用。
so that it does not apply.
实际上，我们不需要这些。
Actually, we don't need any of this.
让我重新装上，
Let me put it back on,
我会评论这一切。
and I will comment all of this.
好的？
Okay?
有了这个，
And with this,
我会离开你
I will leave you
然后我会在下一个视频中见到你。
and I will then see you in the next video.